<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the honourable the knights, citizens and burgesses in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of Oliver Flemming, knight</title>
            <author>Flemming, Oliver, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39776</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">48168274_42881</idno>
  <idno type="VID">42881</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248522080</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1289_PARTIAL</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1288_PARTIAL</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26154</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">48168274</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1308:41, 1925:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the honourable the knights, citizens and burgesses in Parliament assembled. The humble petition of Oliver Flemming, knight</title>
                  <author>Flemming, Oliver, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: British Library and Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Flemming, Oliver.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:42881:1"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the right Honourable the Lords in PARLIAMENT Assembled.</salute>
            </opener>
            <head>The Humble Petition of <hi>Oliver Flemming,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <p>Humbly Sheweth,</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat your Petitioner after <hi>15.</hi> Years service to his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, of ever blessed memory in forraign Negotiations, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving contracted therein a great debt, and being left abroad destitute of all supply for his subsistence, he was forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn houre at such a time as his Majesties own afflictions had made it unseasonable and unpossible for him to expect any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief or recompence, then his Majesties acceptance and Royall compassion of both which your Petitioner had a large and ample Testimony.</p>
            <p>That staying in Town by his Majesties command, he was by an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Lords and Commons put upon the Office of Master of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which he severall times performed to his Majesty (who well knew and considered your Petitioners sad condition) with his favor and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation; yet after an innocent and faithful discharge for several years of his trust therein, he was again <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon that fatall usurpation and change of Government left in a State, much worse then when it was first put upon him, as by the humble Narrative annexed, more fully appears.</p>
            <p>That for the third stroke of this Shipwrack of his fortune, he was threwn upon executing the same Office to persons whom he could not resist and by his own invincible necessities he was forced to act passively. In which his least Misery, was the utter ruine of himself and family, and his only consolation, his constant refusall to repair it, in that detestable way, out of the spoiles of his gracious Majesty, the ruines of the Church, or the deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of private families, although often pressed and urged upon him. Your Petitioner therefore far stricken in years, &amp; out of all imployment, with the so near concernment of a Wise and children, yet unprovided for in extream poverty, humbly begs, that your Lordships would commise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate his deplorable condition, and take into consideration his debts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in the publick service, and order such relief as his extream pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing calamitier require, and as shall seem sit to the Justice, Charity and generosity of the Parliament.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>And Your Petitioner shall pray.</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:42881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42881:2"/>
            <head>THE Humble Narrative OF <hi>OLIVER FLEMMING KNIGHT;</hi> Shewing the manner how I came to execute the Office of Master of the Ceremonies, with my Comportment and sufferings therein, for the space of near 18. Years.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had the honour to serve his late Majesty (of blessed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory) in the quality of his Resident, for the time of 15. years, to the Cantons of <hi>Swizzerland, Grizons, Geneva,</hi> severall <hi>German Princes,</hi> and to some Imperiall Cities; but by reason of the then growing troubles at home, <hi>I</hi> found my self totally abandoned, great Arrears due to me, no mony transmitted for my subsistance, nor could I expect any for the future, and notable to suffer any longer my extream misery, being incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly afflicted, to see his Majesties honour and the publick Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wounded through my sides, I was forced to come home.</p>
            <p>At my Arrivall, <hi>I</hi> acquainted his Majesty with my sad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who was graciously pleased to be very sensible of it, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at that time to help me. I also acquainted his Majesty with some secret Negotiations which I had had; with the Directors of the late Duke <hi>Bernard,</hi> of <hi>Weymors</hi> Army, according to instructions I had to that purpose. Some Propositions were made unto me of great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, concerning <hi>Brisack,</hi> and the rest of the said Dukes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests in <hi>Alsatia,</hi> and other adjacent parts, which I then delivered his Majesty in writing. It did much trouble his Majesty that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture of his affairs then were such, as that he was altogether unable to lay hold on those overtures, so honourable and advantagious. I was commanded to return them thanks for their good will and affection
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42881:3"/>to his Majesty, but they finding themselves destitute of their hopes, were forced to stick close to thir former agreement with <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majesty was then at <hi>Windsor,</hi> when I waited on him; and at his departure thence was pleased to command me to stay at <hi>London,</hi> and to make what shift I could for my subsistance, promising and assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me that when God should restore him to his authority again, he would take care for the payment of my Arrears, &amp; some fiting encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for my long service. He was then also pleased to command me to be vigilant &amp; industrious to keep life in that businesse of <hi>Brisack</hi> and <hi>Alsatia,</hi> hoping that in time he should be in a condition to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it.</p>
            <p>After his Majesties departure, the Ambassadours and Residents continued their Residence in <hi>London;</hi> where having observed from time to time the beginnings, and seen some sad events of our civill Warr, they did successively make their addresses to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>It was then thought necessary, to find out a person fitly qualified, to execute the place of <hi>Master of the Ceremonies.</hi> Some were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to name my self, and so I was commanded by an Ordinance of Parliament, to discharge that place.</p>
            <p>This was done, not only without my seeking, (not having spoken to any friend either for this or any other place whatsoever) but to the contrary; (from a serious desire to be excused from that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in a private station, to attend the good issue of his Majesties Concernments) I did urge some friends of mine, that I might be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensed with, which can be witnessed by persons of eminent quality yet alive. But the Ordinance being passed both the Houses, I did, (not without reluctance, accept of it, and this is the manner of my being engaged in that expensive, and to me ruinous imployment, which I have ever since executed with unwearied diligence, and so far as the calamities of the Times, so full of Distraction, Factions, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and Confusions would permit; constantly managed the things which came within the Sphear of my activity, with all possible pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and dexterity, to the profit and honour of the Nation.</p>
            <p>This puncti<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lious place I was constrained to execute alone, without any help, only when the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> sate, I made use of force Gentlemen of quality, that out of aff<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ction to th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lick reputation did voluntarily assist me, when there was <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick service, during which time, and his Majest<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42881:3"/>commanded upon severall occasions, and to severall places, to conduct Ambassadours to his Majesties presence, who was pleased to approve of those services, and graciously to reiterate his former promises to mee.</p>
            <p>Shortly after, it pleased God for the sins of these Nations, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit wicked men to perpetrate an Act of the greatest attrocity; The King was put to death, with no lesse barbarous cruelty then unheard of insolent ostentation; such as no History can parallell since the Creation. This fatall blow given, and the Peers ignominiously laid aside, and left a Skelliton only of their innate dignity and honours, and the most zealous, faithfull, and prudent Patriots of the House of <hi>Commons</hi> forcibly secluded, and the whole Foundation of the antient Government subverted, a Democraticall Common-Wealth Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for; but in effect it proved to be a Lawlesse and Tyrannicall O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligarchy, which was ingenuously confessed by some of the most Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious amongst them, foretelling that all would come to confusion and ruine.</p>
            <p>Forraign Princes and States send their Ambassadours to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; congratulate this new Government, with great Obsequious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, conforming themselves with great difficultie and aversion, to the capriciousness of those that did manage the affairs, who did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinge all decency and order therein.</p>
            <p>They did send their Emissaries abroad, with great expence and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stentation, accompanied with extravagant Instruction, which was mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of laughter to some of our neighbours. The great concourse of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Ministers, made some of them think it sit to have a committee to Regulate affairs of that nature, and how to manage the publick Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations with forraign Ministers; and what course and form to be established in the distribution of Nationall civilities toward strangers, according to their several Characters and qualities; but no such Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee was appointed. Some were of opinion; that all Ceremonies were sup<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>fluous, that substantialls were to be minded, as if there were no substance in the Transactions betwixt Nation and Nation; That such triviall things might be taken into consideration, according to the emergent occasions. The duty that I owed to the honour of the Nation, begot in me an afflictive resentment of these disorders yet <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nd sincere desire to be as Instrumentall as, I <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> violations thereof, and from a necessity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42881:4"/>which I had no defence, (my then condition considered) I was forced to act in this place, &amp; (to the intent I might better accomplish those publick ends, which I then designed) having more work then I was able to wield, and no Gentlement perswaded to assist me as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, they being weary of that trouble and thanklesse office, I did Remonstrate the necessity of having some help, alledging the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Kings Court, and of all other Courts and Governments, and did instance in Sir <hi>Lewes Lukenor,</hi> who had for his assistance Sir <hi>William Button,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Finnet,</hi> beside a Marshall of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, whose Office was to go before, and to make way at Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and to be sent by the Master, upon ordinary occasions to the publick Ministers. The assistants did officiate in case of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or other necessary absence of the Master but all my endeavors proved fruitlesse. I was told by some of them that they needed no Pedagogue to instruct them. That their Government was of that power and authority, that they could establish things of that nature, without being minded of former examples in <hi>England,</hi> or of what was practised in forraign parts. That I ought to rest satisfied with what orders <hi>I</hi> should receive from time to time, and for to help and assist me they would give order to their Messengers, to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to that purpose; I desired that it might be seriously considered how much it would reflect upon the honour of the Nation, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy men of that condition, breeding, &amp; odious imployment, no wise capable nor qualifi'd to act in a business of such a punctiglious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate nature; That the publick Ministers could not choose but be sensible of such attempts and affronts put upon them; but all I could say was in vain, and as I did foresee, the publick Ministers did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly storm at this indignity, and did make their complaints, but no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse was given, and they calmly at last did indure it with patience, contenting themselves to laugh at our extravagant ways, and despo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall actings, making themselves merly with the gallantry of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants and Jaylors (as they called them) that were appointed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them to their Audience. All which I was forced to hear and see, to my extream grief and vexation, and sometimes taking occasion to speak of these things, hoping thereby to procure a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; I was answered, they were sent, and not sent for, and that they might return whence they came, if not pleased with the government of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Ambassadours came, then on a suddain all things were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42881:4"/>hudled up with confusion and disorder, and acted according to the imperious humor of some few, who with great superciliousness did arrogate to themselvs an infallible knowledge of all State Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and affairs, which others taking for granted, did acquiesse in the judgment of those self-creating State-Grandees, who created also these Innovations in matter of Audience, that it must not be demanded of the Master of the Ceremony, according to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral practise of all Nations, but must be demanded by Letter to the Speaker, when granted, then the Master of the Ceremonies did bring them to the House where being sate, they delivered their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentials to the said Master, and he to the Speaker. In private Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with the Counsel of State it must likewise be procured by Letters from the publick Minister to the President, and then an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Master of the Ceremony to bring him: None were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have Audience in the House, but extraordinary and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Ambassadors, other publick Ministers of lesser Characters, must not be admitted into the House; but a Committee was chosen and sent up to the House of Peers, and the Chair-man received his Credentials from the hand of the Master of the Ceremonies. The House of Lords was not constantly made use of, but sometimes the Inner Court of Wards was appointed, which sometimes did beget Disputes, because they who had not their Audience in the House of Peers, conceived it a disparagement to their Masters, but that which did most justly offend those publick Ministers of the lesser Classis, and in them their Masters, was; That contrary to the practise of the whole World in all the sorts of Government, they were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to deliver their Credentials themselves, to that which was looked upon as the Supream Authority; but when they saw their Complaints and Quarrellings did produce no satisfaction, they were ordered by their Masters to connive at such punctiglios, to the end it might not be an impediment to more material businesses. The publick Ministers in their Reciprocal Visits, would comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they must do in <hi>England,</hi> as those that did reside in <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key, Moscovia,</hi> and other Barbarous Princes Courts, and as to their State Negotiations, that they had as little satisfaction, for they did meet with so many difficulties, delays, unaccustomed and uncivill ways of Treating, that they could not tell how to behave themselvs, their Commissioners being often changed, and so constrained to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42881:5"/>into business, that had been upon the matter already agreed upon.</p>
            <p>The truth is, that the Publick Ministers were generally ill used, unequally and uncivilly dealt withall, the Laws of Nations viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, affronted in their persons, arrested in their Coaches, violent hands laid upon them by Bayliffs.</p>
            <p>An Extraordinary Ambassador from <hi>Ʋenice,</hi> being upon his way hither, had sent some of his goods by Sea, the Ship being of <hi>Holland,</hi> was taken and brought into <hi>England,</hi> and the goods seized upon by the prize Office, the Secretary of that State claims the Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors goods, but no restitution endeavoured. A while after the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors comes himself, and at an Audience prays, that his goods might be restored unto him again, offering to discover some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that had some part of his thing, especially some fair Looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glasses; and had nothing but fair promises, and went away without satisfaction.</p>
            <p>This is but a touch, incidental to this Discourse, it would require a Volume to enumerate the Injuries that have been put upon Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ministers. When great Faults were committed, and of so grosse a nature; that even those who had usurped the Authority, were ashamed of them, then was I made choice of, to excuse and apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gize for them, and desired to take the fault upon my self; Some of the Ambassadors would smile; and say there was a little Civility in the excuse, but that they knew well enough from whom those Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts came. These things were swallowed and dissembled, to the admiration of all those who had any knowledge in Foreign affairs.</p>
            <p>No presents were to be given to Publick Ministers, contrary to the custom of all Nations and Governments; no, not the Warrants for Bucks and Does in their Seasons, as was constantly used to be in the Regal Government; and to the end that this might not seem to be a sordid frugality, it was tempered with an Act of generosity (so called by them) towards Publick Ministers, which was to forbid me to accept of the Donations due to my place, and an odious command laid upon me, not to permit any others imployed in the Service of Publick Ministers, to receive any gratuity from them; but some said that this was a great wrong and injury to me, and that I and others ought to be reimbursed out of the publick purse, which was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, but not performed in the least. With no small d fficulty and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42881:5"/>shamefull sollicitation, the publick Ministers had their wonted proportion of Wines allowed them, Custome and Excise free; but towards the latter end, the Residents were abated a fourth part of their accustomed proportion, all which I was constrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bear upon my heart as matter of much sadnesse and sorrow, having no other comfort lest me, but the constancy and integrity of my endeavours, to prevent the prostituting of the Nations Honour by such miscarriages.</p>
            <p>I humbly conceive, that this rational question may be asked me, why I did Act all this time, and that in all Changes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, whether my reason could dispence and approve of these frequent revolutions? To which I answer in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, for as I was unwilling at first to meddle with this Office, which hath been my undoing, so did I from time to time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse my dislike of proceedings, when and where I could do it with prudence and safety, in a time when the power of the Nation, was weilded with so much passion and violence.</p>
            <p>But my invincible answer is, that Lawless necessity is an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resistable Tyrant, which forced me to act passively, or to perish, for as I humbly shewed in the beginning of this Narrative, I was deeply ingaged for his late Majesty (of ever blessed memory) which debts are since doubled, the Creditors reckoning Interest upon Interest for Twenty Years together, this made my burden so heavy and sad, nay almost unsupportable, that men did admire how I was able to bear it.</p>
            <p>And I seriously considered with my self, that my serving in that place was very innocent, as consisting in holding forth to Strangers the Civilities of the Nation, and indeed, during the whole course of my service in this Office, my end was fixed upon the service, Interest and honour of the Nation, constantly hoping, that God, in his providence would in his good time deliver us out of our distractions, and resettle the three Nations again, upon the ancient Basis, of our former
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42881:6"/>Government, which we see now effected, in great mercy, by the happy return of his sacred Majesty to his Throne. That this is not a flattering insinuation, but a sincere and reall truth is sufficiently known to such, as I durst open my thoughts unto. Besides the duty of my Loyalty, and my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the publiques re-establishment, and therein my own particular concernments were a strong motive thereunto; for I found that I could not expect any Justice, much lesse favour from men that did look upon me, as an old Courtier, and so not much to be trusted, and to this I may adde, the hatred that some leading men did bear me secretly, for having with freedome of discourse expressed my aversion, against Enthusiasts, and their new Heterodox principles in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>I acted all along by the abovesaid Ordinance of Lords and Commons, who had Declared for a King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, during which time, I had the honour to be commanded to conduct Ambassadours to his late Majesties presence, who was graciously pleased to accept of my service, as is above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and I have in all changes, constantly shunned all other Patents, Commissions and powers of whomsoever, which was not without great difficultie and increase of jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie and distrust, which besides the operation it had, in obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the just payment of what was due to my place, did even hinder the reimbursiing of what I was out of purse for their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick service; Nay, their suspition went so far, that some that had the management of State-affairs, did secretly request the publick Ministers, not to acquaint me with their Negotiations, but they frequently comming to visit mee did impart to mee, what had been said to my prejudice, blaming greatly their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, jealousie and ignorance, professing, the greatest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort they had here, was my conversation.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42881:6"/>
            <p> This can be witnessed by many Ambassadours and others yet alive. The necessity of speaking of these things, I hope wil Apologize for this seeming ostentation. I did easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that their drift in revealing those things concerning my self was to have wrought a discontent, and resentment in me, and to have made some use of me to the publick prejudice, which our raw States-men, (not having past their novitiate) did not dive into, and the truth is, that upon this score of revenge and my known poverty, some of them thought, they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten such intimacy with me, that they might attempt to feel how the pulse of my fidelity did beat; not doubting, but their injuries added to my extream necessity, and ill usage would make mee malleable enough for their ends, and to become an Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the furthering of their Masters designs; to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose considerable summs of mony were offered, but were by me refused with a generous Resentment, justly abhorring any thing of that nature, that might any way tend to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shonour or disadvantage of the Nation, or to my particular infamy; I am ready when required, to name the parties. It may easily be conceived, that during the space of so many years, and the constant concourse of so many publick Ministers, and important Negotiations, if I had sought my self, I had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities many and great, to have made my fortune, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, considering that I (almost alone) was permitted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with them dayly.</p>
            <p>When his Majesty (of blessed memory) his goods and moveables were sold, then was I earnestly advised and pressed to lay hold on that opportunity, for the payment of what was due to me, and fitting recompence for my service; the same was offered me, when the Kings, Queens, and Church-Lands were to be sold, to pay those to whom they were indebted, but <hi>I</hi> did loyally, constantly and conscienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously decline and shun those ways of payment and compensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither would <hi>I</hi> meddle with any confiscated particular mans estate, rather choosing extream poverty, then to bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42881:7"/>obnoxious to the Curse of the true Owners; and this I did, in Times, when there was little or no probability, to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to an Accompt by man: I was also told, that I should be imployed on some considerable Ambassie, but in a prudent way, did shun all occasions that might ingage me in any such odious Imployment, although the Allowance was incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably beyond all former precedents, and better paid, being permitted to draw Bills of Exchange upon their Masters, a thing never heard of heretofore.</p>
            <p>Many other great promises were made to me, by the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive powers, but none performed in the least; nor could I ever obtain so much Justice, as to have some appointed to sign my Bills, according to Custom, for the money I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually occasion to disburse for the publick Service. By the Ordinance of Parliament, I was to enjoy the Office, with all the Allowances, Perquisits, Rights, and Priviledges, as hath at any time, or doth belong to any Master of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; which I found did formerly arise by 200. l. Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Fees, an allowance of twenty shillings a day for every Audience, twenty shillings a day for a Coach out of Town, if in Town ten shillings; and besides other incidents, one of the greatest benefits, the right of receiving the accustomed Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Presents from Ambassadors, and other Publike Ministers: But I have not received any of these Perquisites and Rights, belonging to the place, according to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; only I received a great part of the two hundred pound Sallary <hi>per annum,</hi> with great pains, solicitation, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary expence. What I received on that Accompt, will appear on the Publike Receipts; I am out of purse, above a thousand pound for Coach Hire, and a thousand pound for Audiences, and Conferences; and besides the several Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys to his Majesty, for five and twenty Journeys to <hi>Graves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end,</hi> and elsewhere, to fetch in, and to re-conduct Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadours back again; each Journey, computed one with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42881:7"/>another, did cost me ten pound at the least, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the Expensiveness, and distance of the places, and the number of such, as were order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from time to time, to attend that Service. The Donations and Presents due to the place, from Ambassadours and other Publike Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, were courteously sent by them to me, and by me Civilly sent back again. What those Presents did amount unto in so long a time, I cannot exactly set down, but according to my best, and most conscientious estimate, I conceive, that it might amount unto something above five thousand pound.</p>
            <p>I finde my self, after near five and thirty years Publique Service abroad and at home, in this sad and unparalleld Condition, that I am eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pound worse then nothing, although far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath what is justly owing me from the Publique; I have been forced to pawn and sell, what I had of worth, even to my wearing Cloaths. What I have set down in this Narrative (as to the substance of it) I affirm to be a positive Truth, and ready to make Oath upon it, if required. Therefore I do humbly pray, that some present relief may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded me (to prevent my otherwise inevitable Ruine) and that a course may be taken for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging of a Debt contracted in his late Majesties
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42881:8"/>Service Abroad and at Home, in obedience to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Commands, upon an indeclinable necessity.</p>
            <p>I do in all humble manner crave pardon for this Prolix Discourse; but I hope the extremity of my Condition will Apologize for me, and Plead my Excuse.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42881:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>